A Finding Aid to the Jules David Prown Research Material on Artists, 1935-2010, bulk 1958-1975, in the Archives of American Art AAA.prowjule
Archives of American Art
Jules David Prown research material on artists
bulk 1958-1975
1935-2010
AAA.prowjule
Archives of American Art
11.6 Linear feet
Jules David Prown research material on artists measures 11.6 linear feet and dates from 1935 to 2010, with the bulk of the material dating from 1958 to 1975. Prown, an art historian and educator, is an authority on the work of artist John Singleton Copley, and these papers contain related notes, subject files, correspondence, portrait and attribution files, and photographs of artwork. Also found are Prown’s research files on other artists, including Benjamin West, typescripts of his lectures, and copies of his published writings.
Prown, Jules David
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 4 series. The original order of the donor was maintained.
Series 1: Research Material on John Singleton Copley, 1935-2010 (8.6 linear feet; Boxes 1-9)
Series 2: Research Material on Benjamin West, 1967-1990s (1.2 linear feet; Boxes 9-10, 12-13)
Series 3: Research Material on Other Artists, 1950s-2008 (0.4 linear feet; Box 9)
Series 4: Lectures, 1960s-2010 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 10-11)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1960-2000 (0.3 linear feet; Box 11)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Jules David Prown in 2003, 2010, and 2014.
Biographical/Historical note
Art historian Jules David Prown (1930- ) is a Paul Mellon Professor Emeritus of the History of Art at Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut. He is an authority on American art and material culture. Prown is a graduate of Lafayette College and the Winterthur Program in Early American Culture at the University of Delaware. He received his Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1961 with a dissertation on John Singleton Copley. That year he joined the faculty of the Department of the History of Art at Yale University where he was also Curator of American Art at the University Art Gallery and the founding Director of the Yale Center for British Art. In 1966 he published the two-volume John Singleton Copley. While working on the publication he conducted an in-depth computer analysis of Copley’s 240 American sitters. Prown retired from Yale in 1999.
Scope and Contents note
Jules David Prown research material on artists measures 11.6 linear feet and dates from 1935 to 2010, with the bulk of the material dating from 1958 to 1975. Prown, an art historian and educator, is an authority on the work of artist John Singleton Copley, and these papers contain related notes, subject files, correspondence, portrait and attribution files, and photographs of artwork. Also found are Prown’s research files on other artists, including Benjamin West, typescripts of his lectures, and copies of his published writings.
The bulk of the collection consists of Prown’s research material on the work of John Singleton Copley, including notes and correspondence he compiled while working on his dissertation and later two-volume work John Singleton Copley. Of interest are a set of notes regarding the computer analysis of sitters of John Singleton Copley. Included are detailed biographical forms for each sitter and lists of codes and cross references used for Prown's computer analysis. Topics of his notes and subject files include biographical information on Copley, technique and materials, specific works of art such as Watson and the Shark, and painting themes. Correspondence found throughout his research files usually discuss dates of paintings, attribution, and provenance. Photographs and related printed material are often included with correspondence.
Copley, John Singleton, 1738-1815; West, Benjamin, 1738-1820; Art -- Study and teaching; Art historians--Connecticut; Photographs
- Research Material on John Singleton Copley, 1935-2010; Series 1; 8.6 Linear feet Boxes 1-9
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here are Prown’s research files regarding the work of artist John Singleton Copley. Much of this research material was compiled for his 1966 publication, John Singleton Copley. Later documentation primarily concerns attribution. Included are research notes, subject files, correspondence, files regarding portraits and attribution, and photographs of artwork. Researchers should note that lectures regarding Copley are included in Series 3: Lectures, and Prown’s published articles on Copley are included in Series 4: Printed Material.
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged as 6 subseries:
  1.1: Notes, 1947-2007
  1.2: Subject Files, 1949-2006
  1.3: Correspondence, 1953-1999
  1.4: Portrait Files, 1951-2010
  1.5: Attribution Files, 1935-2008
  1.6: Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950s-1990s
  - Notes, 1947-2007; 1.1
    Notes primarily consist of notecards which Prown grouped by subject. Notecards often include attached photographs, printed material, correspondence, and artwork information sheets. Prown filed his notes separately from his other research files, but topics such as attribution, portrait sitters, and other subject files often overlap and all sets of material should be consulted. Also of interest is a set of notes regarding the computer analysis of sitters of John Singleton Copley. Included are detailed biographical forms for each sitter and lists of codes and cross references used for Prown's computer analysis.
    - 1760-1774, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1775-1810, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Paintings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 3-9)
    - "Analysis of Sitters of J. S. Copley, 1753-1774", circa 1960s (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
    - Charles I, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Chatham, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
    - Destroyed Paintings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Diaries, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Discard, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Drawings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Drawings, Attributed, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Drawings, Historical, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Drawings, Multi-Figure Portraits, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Drawings, Portraits, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Drawings, Religious, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Engravings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Exhibitions, circa 1957-2007 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Falsely Attributed or Unlikely, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 1-8)
    - Family Info, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Gibraltar, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
    - Historical Paintings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Insert Material, 1947-2007 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Landscape, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Lynd Sale and Others, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Miniatures, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Mis-attributed to Copley, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Monmouth, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Multi-figure Portraits, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Mythology Paintings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Nativity, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Oil Sketches, Historical, circa 1957-2007 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Pastels, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Personality, Character, Politics, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Pierson, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Portraits, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 4-9)
    - Portraits of Copley, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Portraits, Unchecked Data, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Prices, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Religious Paintings, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Religious and Historical - Attributed, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Religious and Historical - Unlikely Attribution, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Royal Academy, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Surrender to Duncan, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Technique, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Theory, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Unlocated, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Used Notes, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Used Quotes, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Watson, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - West, circa 1957-2007 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Subject Files, 1949-2006; 1.2
    Subject files include draft writings, correspondence, printed material, photographs, notes, and draft writings. Topics include biographical information on Copley, technique and materials, specific works of art such as Watson and the Shark, and painting themes. Subject files are closely related to the notes found in subseries 1.1.
    - Anatomy, 1949-1972 (Box 3, Folder 25-28)
    - Charles I, circa 1960-1990 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Copley Data/Sales, circa 1960s (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
    - Death of Chatham, circa 1958-1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Death of Major Pierson, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Drawings, circa 1958-1991 (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
    - Exhibition at the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Family and Friends, 1959-1992 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Frames, circa 1971-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - General Info, 1996; circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Historical Paintings, 1963-1994 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - House, 1959-1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - "John Singleton Copley and Prints", circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Microfilm, Copley-Pelham Letters, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Mythological Paintings, 1959-1976 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - New Info - American, 1973-1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - New Info - English, 1974-2001 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Offer of the Crown to Lady Jane Gray, 1959-1982 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Other Artists, 1964-2001 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Poetry, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Religious Paintings, circa 1960-1980 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Siege of Gibraltar, 1958-2001 (Box 4, Folder 24-25)
    - Technique and Conservation, 1969-1992 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Victory of Duncan, 1959-1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Watson and the Shark, 1958-2006 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Correspondence, 1953-1999; 1.3
    Found here is correspondence primarily documenting the period during the 1960s that Prown was researching his dissertation and subsequent book on John Singleton Copley. Correspondence is with art collectors, universities, museums, and libraries regarding Copley's works, fact checking, and requests for photographs and permission to publish. Letters are arranged alphabetically by name or location.
    - Correspondence, A-B, 1958-1966 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
    - Correspondence, C-Z, 1953-1999 (Box 5, Folder 1-17)
  - Portrait Files, 1951-2010; 1.4
    Portrait files contain correspondence regarding specific portraits by Copley and often include attached photographs and printed material. Letters discuss provenance, date of the works, biographical information on sitters, and requests to look at the works in person. Documents are arranged alphabetically by name of sitter. Related notes on sitters, including Prown's computer analysis of sitters, can be found in Subseries 1.1 and correspondence regarding portraits with questionable attribution can be found in Subseries 1.5.
    - A, 1958-1987 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - B, circa 1959-2001 (Box 5, Folder 19-22)
    - C, circa 1959-1994 (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
    - D, 1952-2010 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
    - E, 1959-2003 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - F, 1959-2010 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - G, circa 1958-1989 (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
    - H, circa 1959-2008 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
    - J, circa 1964-1984 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - K, circa 1959-2004 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - L, circa 1959-1995 (Box 6, Folder 6-9)
    - M, circa 1959-2008 (Box 6, Folder 10-12)
    - N-O, 1958-1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - P-Q, 1960-1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - R, 1961-1998 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - S, circa 1959-2000 (Box 6, Folder 16-18)
    - T, circa 1958-1990 (Box 6, Folder 19-20)
    - U (Unidentified), 1960-1994 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - V, 1958-1998 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - W, 1951-2010 (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
  - Attribution Files, 1935-2008; 1.5
    Attribution files primarily consist of correspondence asking for Prown's expertise on attributing works to John Singleton Copley. Letters often include provenance details and attached photographs and related printed material. Documents were grouped by Prown according to attribution status and within those groupings are arranged alphabetically by sitter. Additional notes on attribution can be found in Subseries 1.1.
    - Attribution of Paintings and Drawings Unknown, circa 1958-2005 (Box 6, Folder 25-28)
    - Attribution Possible, 1958-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
    - Attribution Probably Okay, 2003-2008 (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
      Includes 1 CD-R of digital photographs
    - "A Checklist of English Paintings Attributed Erroneously to John Singleton Copley", 1966 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Copley Attribution Pending, 1987-1992 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - History, Religion, Myth, 1952-1990 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Not Copley - Drawings, 1966-2007 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Not Copley - English, 1954-1970s (Box 7, Folder 9-10)
    - Portraits, A-N, circa 1950-2008 (Box 7, Folder 11-24)
    - Portraits, O-Z, circa 1950-2008 (Box 8, Folder 1-9)
    - Preliminary Inquiries, circa 1993-2000 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Still Life, circa 1984-1996 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Unidentified Men, 1935; circa 1966-2006 (Box 8, Folder 12-14)
    - Unidentified Women, circa 1964-2007 (Box 8, Folder 15-17)
    - Unnamed Children, Couples, Groups, circa 1972-2004 (Box 8, Folder 18-19)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950s-circa 1990s; 1.6
    Photographs of artwork include copyprints of works by Copley from various museums and art collections. Some photographs include detailed annotations on the verso. Most photographs are arranged alphabetically by sitter or grouped by theme. Miscellaneous photographs found here are unsorted copyprints of works by Copley. Researchers should note that many additional photographs can be found attached to correspondence and notes within the other series in this collection.
    - American Historical Pictures, 1950s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - American Portraits, Miniatures, 1950s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - American Portraits, A-Q, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 22-31)
    - American Portraits, R-W, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Charles I and Monmouth, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Computer Photos, 1960s (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Death of Chatham, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Death of Major Pierson, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - English Historical Pictures, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - English Portraits, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 10-19)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 20-22)
    - Miscellaneous Negatives, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - Religious Pictures, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - Siege of Gibraltar, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 25-26)
    - Watson and the Shark, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 27)
- Research Material on Benjamin West, 1967-1990s; Series 2; 1.2 Linear feet Boxes 9-10, 12-13
  Found here are Prown’s research files regarding the work of artist Benjamin West. Included are research notes, subject files, correspondence, and photographs of artwork.
  - Notes on America, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Italy, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Notes on People, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Notes on People West Knew, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Notes on Historical Painting, Background, Other Artists, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Notes on 1763-1769, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Notes on Benjamin West Sculpture, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Notes on Buckingham House, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Notes on West and Leo III, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Notes on St. George's Chapel Windsor, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Notes on Family, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Notes on House, etc., circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Notes on Personality, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Notes on Royal Academy, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Notes on Studio, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Notes on 1770-1779, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Notes on 1780-1789, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Notes on 1790-1799, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Notes on 1800-1820, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Notes on Other Artists, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Notes on Indians, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Notes on Attitudes Toward and Evaluation of Benjamin West, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - Notes on Portraits of West, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Notes on English Art, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Notes on Addresses, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Notes on Ideas, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 26)
  - Notes on Bibliography Used, circa 1970-1990s (Box 12, Folder 27-28)
  - Notes on Permissions, circa 1970-1990s (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Notes on Drawings, circa 1970-1990s (Box 13, Folder 2-3)
  - Notes on Drawings After 1772, circa 1970-1990s (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Allard Article, 1981 (Box 9, Folder 41)
  - Antiquities of Rome, 1990s (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Attribution, 1977-1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence by Name or Place, 1967-1985 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence by Title, circa 1969-1985 (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - Exhibition, 1978-1983 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Expertise, 1974-1976 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Family, circa 1975-1984 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Historical Pictures, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Indians, circa 1971-1990 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1972-1984 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 10, Folder 13-18)
  - Research, circa 1972-1981 (Box 10, Folder 19-21)
  - Von Erffa (Helmut), 1965-1979 (Box 10, Folder 22)
- Research Material on Other Artists, 1950s-2008; Series 3; 0.4 Linear feet Box 9
  Found here are Prown’s research files on other artists. Files on individual artists typically contain correspondence, photographs of artwork, and notes. Additionally there is correspondence regarding attribution of artwork by various artists, which also include related notes and photographs. Also found here is one file of research essays written by students.
  - Correspondence Regarding Attribution, 1975-1998 (Box 9, Folder 28-33)
  - Photographs of Portraits by Various Artists, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 9, Folder 34)
  - Research by Students, 1986-2001 (Box 9, Folder 35)
  - Joseph Blackburn, 1981; 1978 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Mather Brown, 1964-1988 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Thomas Eakins, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - John Smibert, 1980-1981 (Box 9, Folder 39)
  - John Trumbull, undated; 2008 (Box 9, Folder 40)
- Lectures, 1960s-2010; Series 4; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 10-11
  Found here are draft lectures with handwritten edits, slide lists, notes, and other related documents. Lectures were written for college courses, conferences, and award ceremonies. Prown arranged most of his lectures by subject, but most drafts are annotated with the name of the specific event, location, and date. Many of the lectures are on the subjects of John Singleton Copley and material culture.
  - Associates Lecture, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 23)
  - Bingham Lecture, 1981-1990s (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Chandler, circa 1980s (Box 10, Folder 25)
  - College Art Association, undated; 2010 (Box 10, Folder 26)
  - Colonial Painting, 1967-1996 (Box 10, Folder 27-28)
  - Connoisseurship, Iris Award Talk, 2001 (Box 10, Folder 29)
  - Copley, 1965-2005 (Box 10, Folder 30-33)
  - Copley, 1965-2005 (Box 11, Folder 1-2)
  - Copley and Trumbull, circa 1960s-2001 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Copley Computer Analysis, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Eakins, 1982-2003 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Ethics, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Family Portraits, circa 1990 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Folk Art, circa 1980-1983 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Formalism, 1994 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Furniture, circa 2000 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Heade, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Homer, circa 1983-2006 (Box 11, Folder 12-13)
  - Material Culture, circa 1979-2003 (Box 11, Folder 14-17)
  - C. W. Peale, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - Psychology and Art, circa 1981 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Realism, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Stuart's The Skater, 2001 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Style, 1973-2000 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Benjamin West, 1973-1996 (Box 11, Folder 23-24)
  - Whitney Lecture: Whister, Homer, and Eakins, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Other Lectures, 1966-1996 (Box 11, Folder 26)
- Printed Material, 1960-2000; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 11
  Printed material includes copies of published journal and magazine articles, book chapters, and essays by Jules David Prown. Also found are a few articles on art history written by others.
  - Published Writings by Jules David Prown, 1960-2000 (Box 11, Folder 27-31)
  - Other Publications, 1968; 1979 (Box 11, Folder 32)